hi all good evening guys can you give me some quick thumbs up if I'm audible and visible
okay great let me share my screen
do let me know if you can see the screen share too
seems to be my network is slow today
anyways we'll just speed test
it's very less isn't it
no worries if there's any connection issues we'll change the network
but guys how you doing how's your weekend going on do we have Kiran with us
yeah Kiran your suggestions great great I've seen you some comments in whatsapp
group so just wanted to understand your last message do you mind if I unmute you
and we can discuss over here or you want to take it up in the doubt session I'm
okay with that and thanks so much for answering questions too yeah okay I think
somebody has already answered that question yeah any approach like you can
have you know any number of fixes that you can deal with so even when you you
have to recheck only only one thing like is it is it easy to go and you know
play around with CSS updating it or removing it and adding into the term so
whichever is a costly operation you have to avoid that one and play around with
those things but those are really minute at their level so anything works Kiran
as far as you are understanding in the class we have already discussed that we
can deal with like display block and none or display flex for the for because
we were using flex there okay do you want me to unmute okay let me do that
yeah please go ahead again guys I'm not able to listen if anyone is able to
listen let me know if you're speaking yes I can hear you can yeah so when I
saw that lecture actually I wasn't attending that so I watched the
recording recording I saw that we were trying some different thing like array
making an array then deleting it then recreating it so that was okay but when
we use that for local storage also no then we have to always take care of that
deleting and recreating so that when we are updating the local storage it is up
to date till then so I thought that array would be better if we only use for
local storage and that filtering part will be only just CSS I mean that's what
I think but I don't know what consequences it may have later if there
is a bigger project or some bigger application so I just wanted to know
your views on that yeah so if you see right whenever I'm filtering things
logic I never I didn't play around with the local storage here I was just you
know removing the tickets and recreating whatever needed so when it comes to
filtering logic because you don't really need to apply on local storage like we
don't have any other extra parameter like an object whether to show on screen
or not to show on screen there's no differentiator there if you want to play
if you want to store anything in local storage that way then whenever you are
pushing each and every event into local storage you also have to say that is
this current task is shown on screen or not sure because you again you need a
new variable right so here I'm just using the array two loops one is filter
one is just trying to go for for each and create it yeah I mean whenever we
are trying to create that was a that was I didn't do still that local storage
part but what my idea was that whenever I'll be creating a ticket at that time
I'll put it in this local storage that array and deleting it accordingly so
there will be only two functions which will be interacting with that array so
there will be no other any interactions so will that work it should be working
like there I don't see any challenge like whether the party you said that
whenever we are creating local storage updating we need to check that
currently what are the tickets there so we will be needing an extra variable for
that which that same main content main ticket container we have to recreate
that I mean we initialize that in that function itself but do you know this
like you won't be able to get all the tickets out of local storage and iterate
over it like you have three functions get a set and you know remove so there
is nothing like iteration if you need if you want to go through check locus
was I get and they've get everything out of it but that will be in my just I mean
I rewrite okay yeah I think I think I'm just missing a plot maybe you can
implement and share it with me like maybe we can have a discussion on that
Kiran works okay okay I haven't implemented the local storage part I'll
do that and share in the next session yeah sure works thank you thank you yeah
thank you so I'm muting your back it was Kiran do implement it and let us know
maybe we'll see your implementation and figure out whether it's right approach
to this or that will come to that point we'll discuss like why we need to go
follow one approach or other it would be a great learning for each and every one
for us okay no and thank you so much for taking those questions are a highly
appreciated okay so guys I hope we have good amount of people join the class
today so we'll get started I see we don't need to put any message in the
chat also and thank you all for joining without any messages and for being on
time I'll share my iPad give me a second
guys how many of you enjoyed machine coding problems like the problems we did
all the real-time use cases right maybe a loader maybe in a comment section and
I've also shared in last class I pinned two URLs one was related to you know
many challenges or you can say LLD equations of sample a list of LLD
equations that you can practice other than this thing whatever we have done
it in class and also along with that I've also shared you know JS interview
to get up like you know link where you can go through all the JavaScript
interview questions right I hope you find them I'll add it them in the repo
also for reference so do you keep on like whenever you have bandwidth keep
revising them because I want everything to be present in repo I'll try to do
that okay great so nice and there's a so today's class is mostly like we'll start
with something called as on a top level I won't go into this keyword completely
because we have three classes specifically for understanding this
keyword in depth okay but today we'll understand on a top level like a
different meaning for a sink and we'll try to explore that but other than that
thing right so the few important topics that we have to discuss is set timeout
so and then we'll understand something called as debouncing and there will
understand trottling and there are two keywords that are specifically used in
HTML whenever you link new scripts right when I say scripts it can be JS or CSS
file or any other file whenever you link a script into the HTML you will be
finding there is something like async or defer keyword added to them so we'll
understand these two keywords okay so this is going to the context today and
these are like really important for interview specific also from theory and
trying to understand it because this this these two solutions are applied to
many of the LED questions I mean the concepts will be applied for them okay
so we'll explore them I'll try to keep it as simple I'll pick really simple
examples as much as can be so that we are sure that we grab the concept of it
and then we'll move on before that I just want to know how many of you
understand know what sent interval does we have discussed this in last class but
I just want to know what set interval does are you clear with this point what
set interval does I see one thumbs up okay frequency of execution okay can I
say this way that set interval is an higher order function which executes a
callback function after every interval and every interval is the second
parameter that it takes and this this is interval time right can I say it this
way guys like what the set interval does no let me so you know the other set
time set interval and set timeout are a browser API actually browser provided
higher order functions they are providing for us and you can view you
will be able to access like if you go right into any browser you go into the
console and try to do window dot like set timeout you'll be able to see it's
part of a window object or else you can also access like directly set timeout
because everything out of the global object you can access directly okay this
is something that its implementation behind the scenes implementation you
can always see like what is the implementation of set timeout okay so
these are the two things provided by browser so we'll explore today what does
set timeout does now as we know that we have one is for interval which will
execute like after each and every interval at each and every interval
whereas set timeout is an again a higher order function which executes a
callback function after this timestamp or let's say you can say this is the
delay here we say that once you trigger any function this particular function
higher order function it will call this callback function after some time did
you understand this difference calling once and calling after every interval
the basic difference on top level let's say this is also five thousand when we
say five thousand five seconds now if this is a timeline let's say zero
timeline then you have five seconds then you have ten seconds then you have 15
seconds now just let me know if I execute set interval how many calls I
will be making it here when I use site interval if this is the time let's say
we have this 15 seconds right firstly at here then you'll have second then you'll
have third right I hope you understand when it comes to set timeout when it
comes to set timeout
so here even though we have all the timelines 0 5 10 15 it will execute only
once after the delay of 5 seconds I hope on like your definition of set timeout
and interval is clear this is clear we'll try to go and see some of the use
cases examples like just hands on right let's say I create a class 20 I call
this as set timeout dot HTML and let's say firstly we'll try to actually I
wanted to do some animation logic I'll try to show like how that is how it's
different you know what is the difference between this let's say I have
a H1 tag I can say set timeout and set interval okay then I can say that let's
say I'm having a container div inside that I say I'm the dev and let's say I
have a button which is stop the animations okay nothing much interesting
guys here till now let's say copy this whatever is there inside I copied as a
document title and let's say I have a style sheets for this one and I just
have a div tag inside that I'll select a particular height and width let's say
height to be 100 pixel and width to be 100 pixel and let's say background color
to be tomato let's say we have this and let's make this as 50-50 as of now and
we'll render this one once open with live server no let me go here in the
browser let me open this one now so what I'll try to do is that if you I'll show
it for two differences specific differences let me get an access to this
element firstly here I'll add a script tag inside this const let's say div
document dot query selector let's say I can directly call it as a div since I am
not using any CSS classes and we have only one div here and let's I also say
that button document dot query selector button fine once we have this div now by
default what I want to do is let's say if I use set interval now inside set
interval I'll write some logic but let's say I do it at every two seconds okay
firstly I'll try to output console dot log from set interval and what I'll do
it here is that I'll get an access to this I'll use this div and I'll play
around with its width okay now how can I do it I can just say that div dot let's
say I say the current width how do I can get the width guys do you remember
do you remember how we can get the width that is for up let's say let's say that
let's move this move it here and put a debugger I'll have it here I'll refresh
it once I have it here let's say dev dot style dot width not getting anything as
of now if I want to get width what could be the better thing once I have this
div can I go to class list I don't have classes applied think of it this one
guys how can we access the width because we applied here we didn't have CSS like
the CSS that is applied directly is on to the item level container right rather
than a CSS class like you can explore this one here once you go inside the
body you have it here you see it here background color has been added to this
step okay let's say okay but we haven't added any event here we don't have any
target element okay let's say some chase like dev dot get attribute now what
attribute you want to get it because I don't have any attribute added here on
this step we don't have any attribute okay so let's let me let me do this
thing let us go back and add a one CSS class called dev and let's say if you
are able to make it instead of dev let's say container adding it as a
container no once I do this I go to sources I try to remove this debugger
refresh it once I have here I'll say that dev dot style dot let's see if I
still getting it I'm still not getting it again going back a dev dot class list
dot okay once I get an access to this container I can only get the class but
how can I get the value anyone can anyone think of it any idea how we can
get the current width can anyone think of it
okay let's say I said a dev dot get attribute if I do get attribute let's
say okay dev dot get attribute now inside this what should I pass I should
pass container sorry I should pass class I got the still you know the values
container but I didn't get any CSS values okay I leave it to you guys
explore this one so for now what I'm going to do is like when I'm going for
this interval okay what I'll declare here is that let's say I have a one
width let's say I say this is a 50 pixel okay okay once I have this I'll get that
dev dot style dot width okay I'll try to make it each time whatever width I have
it let's say I remove this one what I do is that I'll multiply two into the
current width plus I'll add pixels also I'll update this width I should be doing
after updating it
okay now the animation that I wanted to show you it was like just let's say if
this is working fine do you see this after each and every
interval this width is getting automatically added I mean even if I
refresh it this like looks like again a loader right now but if you want to
stop this if you want to stop this you know like whatever is playing behind
the scenes what if we want to stop this how we can stop this case last class we
learned it like how we can stop the interval let's say I can say store it
in a here okay what I can say is that if if width is greater than let's say each
time it's multiplying let's say I say that 500 then I can say that clear
interval I can pass intervals here okay so this event how many times should it
execute
think of this thing is how many times it should execute currently we have till
width is less than 500 we started with 50 at 50 width so it multiplied it became
100 100 become 200 200 became 400 only three times right now let's see if this
is okay let me refresh now once twice three okay four times now why did it
happen four times because it fourth time it it came till here then it
verified a condition and once condition was satisfied it cleared its interval
right so I hope this set interval logic do you understand how does it work okay
now then there is another way that if you want to stop let's say using I have
a button now okay when I click someone clicks a button add event listener now
let's say I have this one of the ways to clear interval is like once whenever
someone is clicking a button I'll say that clear interval interval okay so
what if I come stop this now if you see it's continuously progressing but once
I click this it will stop so like I just I just wanted to give you some more
hands-on like how this thing works now I'm going to replace this logic with set
timeout right just I hope you understand this animation like interval and no
difference between that let's say I copy this thing I copy this thing and I say
that this is timeout okay I use this instead of clear interval I can use
clear timeout and I can I have to update this as a variable this one and I can
remove this I can I can say that directly apply width of since it will
execute only once let's say a 400 pixel okay now let's see if this is working
okay okay this thing is still executing so let me stop this refreshing it it
happens only once it updates only once okay so this is just an overview of this
thing guys how do you actually use it and what can be the one of the use case
where you want to play with on its set timeout on interval I hope this is we
were anyways clear with the theory part I just wanted to show in real-time how
can you use this clear interval and clear timeout events also is this clear
one final check if this is clear will go with the debounce concept great so let's
start with something called as debounce
so then there is a one of the you know famous question how many of you have
know that what is type ahead what how many of you know this keyword something
called as type ahead
or let's say auto suggest
this is one of the famous high-level HLD interview questions you will be
learning this one in HLD curriculum but you know there's a concept so this HLD
curriculum whatever we'll be covering was let's say behind the scenes in the
back end so we have to handle some use cases in the front end too so we'll
cover today here one of the example where we leverage something called as
debouncing concept this might be something like sounding like a crazy
what I'm talking about but if I'll take you to the one of the famous websites
like Flipkart and I'll show you not exactly trice yeah trice is a behind-the-scenes
algorithm how do you search it and get it but I'm talking in terms of front end
let's say if I go here and if you see when I say auto suggest or something
like even if I go for Google search right Google search let's say I come
here now if you go and see right each time the search is like when I click it
I'm loaded with few of the suggestions already now where these are suggestions
coming from like if you see these suggestions what what what is the
solution this thing is they are they are applying if you go and see in this
site local storage now if you see it here it is google.com they should be
having this data stored here
okay these are not these are static G static but it should be there in local
storage itself maybe I
not sure why this is not expanding let me try to get the value no let's look at
this one whatever Google search is doing it's
preloading with the some suggestions right Arjun they spoil a bubonic flag or
organ happy Valentine's day wishes course so these are the top most
searched content like KL University Vijayawada, IITJ events results, Jordan Poole,
Swiss Parentals right, Modi UAE visit so these are the most searched content so
what Google is doing like instead of you typing it down it filters out right
let's say once I do this it is giving me some suggestions on
base of that right so these are the pre loaded you'll understand why this thing
works this way but my point of question here is that let's say I've come to this
one of the website flipkart which you might have used in day-to-day life more
and now if I search something let's say a mobile okay let's say search mobile I
just wanted to look at this particular you know API calls which are triggering
for the auto suggest no I filter here auto suggest okay let's say auto suggest
no this has triggered so many calls now let's say what is the keyword exactly
being sent in the payload if you see first it sent for M then it's sent for
mobile which I you know corrected back it went for a movie it went for movie it
went for mobile like do you see like one of the thing is that even if I type down
bigger keywords let's say I remove this one okay
let me clean it up let me just select something big big item guys let's say
washing machine no I typed on such a big thing here and I let's say if you see
how many API calls being made for the suggestions whatever you see it in the
drop down there are only two two API calls been done one is like with W one
is done with washing machine whole thing so do you see this like this is
something where deep on sink comes such that whenever you keep on because this
is an input element right do you agree that this is an input element and there
might be some event listener added to this one and this event listener is
always looking for something like key up once user lifted once user lift any
particular key once you press it like I click W the key is up API call should be
made once I type a key is press keys up again and another API call should be
made okay so if you see for each letter from the logical point of view if you
think from behind the scenes there should have been more than 20 25 API
calls right triggering because we are listening to each and each and every
keyword you know so the what they are doing is they're trying to reduce the
amount of API calls so this is where the optimization comes in like how do you
optimize the amount of API calls you are making when user is trying to do
search something right so feel will figure it out like does it assume the
interval or anything but let's create that problem first okay whatever problem
I talked about like on each keyword you should be able to make an end goal then
we'll figure out from end calls to reduce the amount of course now let's go
to the code first let's build this step by step I'll use something like simple
def I'll say that search okay then let's let me convert this into a label okay
inside this I'll also have an input element and since it's a let's say I
also give a placeholder search here and let's say I go to CSS I add some CSS to
this one just like giving a diff again let me open this on the right side just
trying to build a box a basic CSS display flex align items center justify
center see whatever there's a gap gap of five pixels across then once we have
this which I also have a border of five pixel solid black lavender let's say we
have this also I add some padding to it of 20 pixel okay now once I have this
let's say if you also have something border radius like 8 pixel now once we
have this let's say also I give some margin around it let's say margin would
be 20% of the screen so that I move items into the center nothing much
interesting is how basic thing that we used to do but what I'll do it here is
that I'll go with the usual flow that we can write it out so let's say I have
this const input I'll try to get an access to this input element document
dot query selector once I have this now since I'll let's say I give an input
directly and I'll add a listener to this one input dot add event listener and
something we are looking for is key up once user lifts the key okay or key up
is something deprecated so let's say we say the key down once user is entering
something as soon as that will call something okay now let's say since it
takes us some you know callback function let's say make an API call now
this function let's say console dot log says that making an API call so we are
actually not firing it up but we are trying to see that behavior that's I
provide this callback function here okay now let's go back launch this in
exact browser that we have open with live server can we console log target
also yeah we can do that target what value so that you will be able to see
that for each thing that we are trying to output I'll do that let's say I have
event console dot log event dot target dot value okay now once I come here I'll
try to launch this one now let's go to console now if you see it here if I type
let's say if I type some bits name S A M B I T do you see that for each keyword
we are making N calls like whatever however things however however the
items we are typing it down those in my number of API calls has been triggered
now is this a performance issue or not first let me know if whether this is a
problem or not in real time if you implement let's say you are a front-end
developer and you are given a backend API that hey once you give this keyword
we'll search and we'll give you some list of suggestions that you have to
show it in the drop-down in search field okay but if you keep on making API each
time user clicks first API takes some time to load that data and give you back
and there will be N number of calls you might be triggering in the network
which is like using so many resources behind the scenes right and it's like
we have to limit the number of API calls right that's our basic idea any idea any
ideas guys like how we can you know stop this from happening from the current
knowledge we have in the current knowledge we have any idea like or else
let's think of from basic point right when we should make an API call actually
when we should make an API call once user stop typing should we make an API
call or after user keep typing we should make an API call what could be the right
way of making an API call in search
when user stop typing when a full meaning like okay so some bit says that
time interval of five seconds after key up something like that once user stopped
okay so this basic idea is clear right now what we are saying is that on top
level from this problem statement that we are making N calls here so once user
is like he's a typing typing typing typing now once he stops will calculate
some of interval of time and once even in that interval if you didn't type it
anything will trigger with whatever event value is right let's say he's
typing typing typing typing continuously typed and then he stopped and will
start once he stops will load that interval time and once this interval is
expired will make an API call only once so if we're typing four five keyword four
five keywords are hardly let's say he's typing five words like automatic washing
machine
now depending on users right ability how fast they are on keyboard or how fast
how slow they are so we have to adjust the interval such a way that it should
allow the user to type it everything and we optimize it so it's our call that how
we tune this interval the time okay now let's see like how we can implement this
one will go step by step okay let's say I I write one higher order function okay
I write an higher function calling it as debounce function call okay function
API call let's say we call this one this name maybe not a right way but let's say
this takes a function let's say I cannot say this keyword and then also you have
some delay okay once you have this once you have this what you will do is that
let's say you try to execute you try to execute this one such that you have a
set timeout you call this function you execute this function after that delay
of 3,000 seconds let's say three we are tuning it to the two seconds once user
stop after two seconds we'll make an API call now what I'll do it here is that
I'll instead of calling a make API call I'll call something like debounce
function API call inside that I'll pass make API call and I'll also pass the
delay of let's say 2,000 seconds okay and accept the delay here no so this is
what we can think of like we want to once user stops typing if we want to
make an API call after that delay is expired so some some one of the best
function to use a set timeout isn't it like we have to call only once and only
after the delay is expired that logic is clicking you guys because you have
suggested me that we have to make only after user stops typing
let's see if this is working fine or not first okay let's see if this is working
fine or not now once I go back and let's say I typed on everything okay let's let
me try to type down here still I'll try to type Kiran's name now let's say I
typed on Kiran name okay let me see this has broke or what's wrong with this
let's say I'm calling okay I shouldn't have called this function I should just
only pass a function because it's a callback function that executes my word
now let me go here and try to type down Kiran let me see if this is working
fine okay I don't see API call coming here did I mess up anything here let me
check okay it's it's working fine now let's say comment this for now like
since just say let me comment this thing for now or let's say I add this thing
itself no optional training they shouldn't create an issue now I make
something like call some bit it's not calling that function again again is it
not passing parameter for API okay just a second
zero says that not passing parameter to API function no it shouldn't create a
problem that way like we should be able to access this even then and I'm just
thinking like let's say each time we are passing an API call we are making a
callback function here building it now what what's the difference would be like
if I pull it up and paste it here it should be anyways executing that one
right so in line number 36 I didn't get your point this not passing parameter to
API function this one event you want to say this event is it that shouldn't be
a problem but let's see if the way this is this isn't working to repartee if I
typed on even repartee now each time this listener is clicking let's say just
nothing is working as of now let's say if I try to refresh it okay maybe this
particular line might be creating an issue because I'm getting an undefined
check let's I make this simple fix now once I typed on even then no API call is
being made or nothing is executing it here okay let me refresh it what could
be the issue here once I have this listener it goes here I have received a
make API call function which is which is just a callback function that we should
execute and when I'm passing the delay no right now each time I am typing this
something keyword this listener should listen to it isn't it this listener
should listen to it like a key down event let me refresh this one I am not
exactly sure what's wrong here basic code writer basic lines of code now
let's say I pull it up this one I keep it below only not to be actually should
be on top itself but is anyone able to think what can be the mistake here any
idea
okay let me do one thing I'm not trying able to replicate which I didn't save
this code I again saved it but each firstly it adds a listener that's a
key down listener that's great and this we are the same thing we have called it
and it's taking two things now it passes the expected delay initially it executes
that one then if I type down why this event is not triggering
this is odd
so I say
key down event accepts API as a param but you're calling API just a second I'll
try to understand your point here maybe we need to return the timeout function
let's say that okay let's say I try to return this okay what if we I try to
return it add event listener event target parameters is not type one object
this is fine event is not getting passed to the debounce as param not to call
API function let's say guys I have a piece of code let's see that and
implement this one if it is working fine okay I let's say this is something that
I have written an old class let's say this is an function a callback function
that I have again I do this same logic let's say if I replace here input with
this logic I use it right here okay then I also have something like this function
which I don't want to use it here let's say comment this particular thing and I
also particular this one now let's say instead of this thing returning what if
I return directly as you say return set timeout a function and delay okay I hope
this thing works now still I get an error now I see that number of API calls
are made zero okay let's say I call it inside this one whatever function is
being returned let's say this function is being returned and it's a remove this
timer okay let's understand this thing why did I mess it up here firstly try
chat GPT got it this anyways firstly let's see this why this was not working
earlier so hmm basic mistake so so if you see this this is an higher-order
function where we passed and function and it in order to execute any callback
function like it will be where we should have been returning a function rather
than executing this one somehow but I I'll get back to this logic why this is
working now why not later but let's come back and try to see this one okay that
if you see it again if I typed on each and everything now let's see if I'm able
to access the event also in this function that I have event I try to make
a console log so dot log of even dot target dot value
now let's say I type down some bits okay I am NOT able to get that target value
here or event is not being passed that that something will fix it but let's
say I try to remove it as of now but on a top level I again coming back to this
thing guys whatever I messed up in last ever it's let's figure out that one
later but if you see if I type down a list of six keywords I'm still making
the six API calls now one of the way to you know optimize this call optimize this
one is that pretty straightforward and simple is that what we'll do here is
that we'll use something logic like clear timeout implementation let's say
if I comment this thing remove this thing out and I store it here in a timer
now let's understand firstly at what's happening here line by line if you see
let me write down I in the iPad and try to show what is exactly being done here
so firstly the function that we are returning is having a clear timeout
and we are removing something called as timer okay and we are storing inside
this timer like actual value like this set timeout where we are calling this
callback and with the delay right this is something we are doing it as of now
but let's see how we will be able to apply this first let's understand how
does set timeout works because if you go and see JS files right if you see JS
files what type of language we can call it as JS okay showing browser sorry
guys I again maybe right I hope you are able to see this this function whatever
I have written and okay now now think of JS guys what type of language is that
JS is it single threaded or multi-threaded is it single threaded okay
how many of you say that it's single threaded give me thumbs up for single
threaded and give me thumbs down for multi-threaded or let me know like if
you do you understand what is single thread versus multi-thread I hope you
understand the difference between these two things no idea what threads okay
good no worries now have you watched movie Shivaji Rajnikanth movie now once
he become a don he signs with both the hands right all the documents which are
admission letters for the students he signs with both the hands do you
remember like at same time he's you know doing multi-processing like multiple
things so what what happens in single threaded language is something it focus
on only one thing at a time when it comes to multi-threading it has ability
to focus on multiple things okay to do simultaneously do you understand this
parallel no parallel word like parallely I can do multiple things now when it
comes to single it's like only one thing at a time I hope you got the basic
difference what is single threaded and versus multi-threaded you know if you
know even for the multi-threading languages you can spawn you can spawn
when I say spawn I mean to say that you can create like how many threads you
want that many that you can create in an application when it when you go for
something language like go or C++ or Java they have ability to you know
multitask and you can create like good amount of threads depending upon your
hardware setup how much CPU you have how much but there again even if you go in
depth you will see something like there is a locking mechanism how would you
handle all those things but not a point of concern as of now JS is something is
JS is single threaded language when I say this now single threaded language I
hope you are able to understand that JavaScript does only one thing at a
time if I'm eating food I'll only eat food if I'm writing something I'll do
only something one thing if I'm right reading one part one line of code I'll
read only that line of code I won't be able to read other lines of code is this
clear what JS is now also along with single threaded we also say that it is
synchronous you also say that this is synchronous single threaded language I
added a key another keyword guys now think of it what you can say that
synchronous when I say something like in sync like I'm actually in sync when I
say that generally is that you know again synchronous single threaded are
like both the both are talking about same thing but when it comes to think
like one did they are just talking about both things are like one thing at a time
and when I say synchronous is basically that let's say it's executing a piece of
line it will keep on executing that line once only if this is executed it will
go to next slide and it in JS something pass execution happens from top to down
that we already know isn't it so I hope all this discussion is clear till now
whatever we did about JS language now let's understand what set timeout is
doing or anything we know that earlier we talked about something like happening
in JS let's say your JS code is being passed passed passed and suddenly you
found set timeout and let's say there's a callback function and you have a delay
of three thousand seconds or three thousand milliseconds now once you see
this one and there is a call stack all the things are getting executed and
there is suddenly set timeout now tell me what should actually happen now all
the execution should stop right below code execution stop till this three
thousand seconds are elapsed and this thing is executed nothing should be
working in application right from the definition of JavaScript how many of
you are agreeing with this point like there shouldn't be anything executed
until this three seconds are elapsed and this callback function is executed
right but is this actually happening is that easily is it actually happening what
if I go with set interval imagine set interval like let's say set interval I
say that every five thousand seconds well it executes after five thousand
seconds and it should be keep on executing this piece of code itself it
should not execute the other lines of code right below logics so this would be
a bottleneck for an application isn't it if this is what actually how JS works
right if if like if if you're reading from top to down and you can do only one
thing at a time and if you got stuck here and you're not able to move ahead
then all the other functionalities of your application will be stop right okay
so guys what I was talking about is that firstly is this keyword is clear to you
is this clear keyword clear to you think of a single-threaded language no let's
say you have a piece of code top to down you are keep on reading and in
suddenly you have set time out and there is a callback function and you have
delay and you also have a below some piece of code and when you are
executing when this code is getting excluded in call stack line by line in
execution context okay now all these lines are executed now when when you
encounter this particular line in call stack now since this says that one thing
at a time and in a synchronous way it's a single thread it should be waiting for
this delay to expire and then call execute this callback function creating a
sub execution context only then it should be able to execute below files
isn't it this is what our understanding should be with respect to but what I'm
asking that is it happening that way when you go for something like set
interval instead of let's say set timeout what if there has been set
interval if you had something like set interval and you have a callback
function and let's say you have interval time given now because this is
should be executed once on one time after the other till you clear this
interval the execution will be struck right I mean your application will hang
there isn't it but we are seeing something is that application is working
fine application is working fine somehow so what's actually happening in behind
the scenes right so now all this higher-order functions like set timeout
okay or set interval or are your API calls whichever are like time taking in
nature okay whichever are time taking in nature which let's say it's it might not
be executed right moment but it takes some time so what happens is that
whenever this call stack encounters this use cases right what it does it it takes
out from the call stack put it in some sort of queue let's say timeout one say
interval one say API call one and it stores in the queue only when let's say
when this timeout is expired when I mean say when a deal is expired what it does
is it put backs into the call stack to execute it and when it only when it
would be only able to put is that when this call stack is empty and there is
nothing being executed that moment only then this timeout function water will be
put back and the callback function will be executed similar way once this
interval is like put back it will see that it will call that execute that like
callback function again it will put back into the queue you understand that
rotation what is happening behind the scenes actually guys how many of you are
able to connect with me if there is someone who don't understand this
concept let me know because future classes will be really dependent on this
logic okay okay no no what I mean to say is that let's say there are this events
are based on some time isn't it let's say timeout will execute after some
delay or interval happen after some time and API call will also say take
some time to execute now when these things are happening right now we cannot
we cannot wait for that time because if we wait for that time other part of the
code will be hanged let's say someone is clicking some other events in the
application the listener should be able to listen right okay so they what
basically behind the scenes are happening is like that JavaScript is
removing this this functions like timeout interval from the call stack it
is putting into some of the queue okay one queue and it is waiting this all
things are waiting waiting for what waiting for the timeout the delay or
interval whatever you have given or this API to fetch data from back end
once this time or delay is execute are done then these things are put back into
call stack back into this one so to execute it is this clear guys how that
set timeout and set interval works behind the scenes now this actually is
a part of something called as event loop which will further go in depth which
will go further in depth to understand this one we'll come back to this topic
again we'll explore this one okay so meantime app will be stuck so in mean
times app shouldn't be struck app will only struck when your call stack is
stopped when I'm when call stack is like okay to move forward then it it won't be
stopped right only when call stack is empty this things will be put back I'll
show you that guys I'll show you that one okay let's say no firstly let's let's
come to this one what I'm generally doing it here okay okay firstly let's
understand this logic what's happening now inside this deep bounced I'm
initializing a timer I am putting it to the clear timeout I'll explain this code
I'm coming to this logic okay let's understand this function what's
happening okay I gave some delay like let's say I've gave some delay like 500
milliseconds 0.5 seconds and I say that once you call any user let's say any
user is typing any key event let's say is typing any keyword let's say typing
this th is when is typing it each time we are calling this function and we are
initializing this variable and we are checking we are checking if this clear
timeout if there is any set timeout exist clear that timeout if like if
there is only thing or exist then clear it and then after attach a set timeout
to this timer a variable and execute it now when again let's say this is
happening let's say if I type down t here okay if I type down t here for the
timer there is nothing undefined there's nothing is there okay so it won't do
anything as of now but let's say if I execute this timer and go to the next
line let me you know this is not persisting data but what I'm generally
trying to say it here is that if you see this function if you see this function
whatever we have written let me cut this one
so what I'm saying is that now let's say in call stack okay for each and each
listener right each listener whenever key down event is fired key down event
will be fired for let's say if I typed on some bit it will fire for this one
this one this one is also six times it will fire isn't it it will fire that one
at least now inside this we are calling this debounce timer this function is
being caught now when we call this function we are passing some delay and
a callback function to execute now let's say what I'm trying to do it here is
that I am here having a variable timer in memory and once this set timeout has
been put into the call stack right it has been removed it is put it into the
queue here okay for the first letter s now when again user types a when user
type say I'll come here I'll check whether in memory there is something
attached to the timer so we see that this existing timer is attached to this
keyword so we'll say that can you remove the existing timer clean it up so when
in second event this will be cleaned up and there is nothing okay then once this
is cleaned up again you would take it a event and you make again a set timeout
call okay now again you store it a value into the timer now you have set timeout
for a event and this is again put into here queue and this is again removed
from here okay now again it goes when you type M when you type M again let's
say when you type M you again call the set timeout here before calling the set
timeout you'll check whether there's anything timer exist yeah you see that
this is existing please remove this one also clear it so as you do it keep on
doing it you will come at a point where you will type something like T and you
will stop when you stop it when you keep on cleaning up and when you stop it at
final point right when you stop at this final point there is no one going and
coming out and clearing this event from this queue there is no one clearing out
and once the deal is done it will put into the stack and execute and make an
API call are you able to relate like actually what's happening behind the
scene when you do debounce so all the events whatever are being added into
this queue right whatever being are added first we are clearing all the
older events all the older events function calls are cleaned up okay all
the fun ones like one after the other we are cleaning up only the last set timeout
will persist here and that will be executed because for that time will
elapse and it will get X I hope you understand how debounce works guys how
many of you are still facing challenge understanding this one let me know okay
now if you see it now if you see it how many things we are making like let's say
if I try to type down let's say I typed on my name let me remove this debugger
now let's say if I go and type down clean it up this one I'll refresh it
let's say I typed on my name you see I made only one request like number of
requests count to zero now let's say I typed on something like washing machine
okay I'll type on something like washing machine to see only one API call what if
I want to type down again automatic you see three API calls max how we are able
to optimize this one because we are each time a new event is added we are
clearing the existing events and then we are setting our time with a new the
existing one is this clear guys how this is working I hope you are able to
relate like how this actually works okay but the now one of the most important
use case right when it comes to debounce is like it's really important topic when
you want to actually optimize for you know like this sort of search filter
logic logics because you want to preserve that you know the amount of
API calls you're trying to make it fresh because each time you are making a fetch
you are actually pulling six kilobytes of data over the network and it is
transferred from the somewhere system which is put down on the back ends at
behind the scenes right so that optimization we are doing it here okay
this is what debounce helps us so we'll come back after the break we'll explore
like what throttling doesn't does it okay so do you need break or can I go
ahead by taking like class I need 20 minutes to explain okay break okay let's
take break of six minutes guys I'll give six minutes but before that let me know
are you able to follow up are you able to follow up guys like did you
understand how debounce works behind the scene how set time out on set interval
works those are removed from call stack put it into some queue and will
understand this thing all those things in depth when we pick event loop I'll
show you mechanically how those things won't works and debugger tool and
everything and those are executed once times are elapsed it put back into the
call stack you call stack to execute it okay let's come back in six minutes
you
guys is everyone back
give me some sir if everyone is back I just want to explain one of the bug that
I was doing and not able to figure out I just was thinking you know for this
four five moments and I do remember here while I was trying to execute set
time or directly instead of returning a function it was not working I was not
able to figure out then but I was thinking in two minutes of time I you
know the moment the the bug here that was created was like whenever you are
really creating a listeners right you are not actually calling a function but
you are writing a callback function attaching a function to it do you
understand the difference between calling and attaching a function to it
it works like a callback function right now whenever I was actually calling this
T bonds and our function I was actually executing this part but it will be only
executed one time but if I want to attach that function I have to know when
if you see this what logic is the happy forming here it is returning a function
and this whatever that function is written will be attached to this key
down event and whenever key down is there this function will be executed is
it it so that's the difference I was making a mistake so I able to understand
what's a mistake I was committing there if there is anyone who don't understand
give me thumbs up thumbs down and explain that thing guys I hope okay see
many people now okay yeah yeah right so let's say whenever you write any event
listener whenever you write event listener okay let's say what could be
the common thing you like a click event okay and you define a callback function
right this is a syntax of it isn't it isn't it this is a syntax of it when you
write it now let's say I write a console dot log console dot log and I let's say
I'm trying to print the event whichever I'm receiving let's say event no I am
defining a function inside the listener but am I executing this function here or
I'm just defining the function declare I'm doing the function declaration only
know writing the definition of function but I'm not calling it I will be only
calling this function when I do this isn't it defining a function and calling
it right away I able to understand the difference between attaching a function
to the listener versus call executing that function now earlier like here in
the listeners we attach a function let me write a cut callback function but we
don't execute it manually that will be taken care where I actually went
function but earlier what I was doing is that if you see I was calling the
debounce optimized function instead of doing here anything I was trying to set
timeout and I was doing function and delay this is again as the principle of
listener right what I'm doing it I'm just calling that function on each click
I'm executing that logic isn't it I'm executing this function are you able to
understand the difference like when actually we should have been attached a
callback function instead of that they are executing a function now when I
return a function here when I return a function from this function this
particular return function is actually being attached to this listener is this
clear guys and I can write down in simple keywords if I have to do it what
actually have been doing it is that let's say this is a keyed-on event now
once keyed-on is event is there like let's say we have this callback
function now here we were doing that same thing let's say I have a timer now
the timer should be art added on the top let's say I can add a timer here let's
say I have a timer here declared okay once I have a timer what I'll do is that
I'll copy this one these two things instead of writing like this function
and delay I'll actually call it opt function and I'll say that 500 okay this
is same as this both lines are actually doing same thing are you able to relate
it now instead of attaching earlier I was calling this guys is this clear
point give me thumbs up thumbs down if you are able to understand it now so for
listeners we attach yeah yeah right somewhere like if you go for any code
let's say we go to Kanban board we have too many events added right now do you
see this we are writing only declaring the function but we are not calling the
function for the double-click event or you go for any other event like let's
say if this particular event how how function function executes only when you
call right let's say I declare a function like function some and I pass
a comma B only then like doesn't matter right that won't execute until as you
call them so calling is not my headache that listener will take care of it
that's what yeah yeah so I hope you got the bug that I was creating and it just
clicked me right moment I just wanted to explain you guys like what could be the
mistake what was the mistake actually okay let me remove this lines of code
no so I hope debounce is clear right to everyone debounce is clear like how does
it work debounce so whenever you want to do whenever you want to do something
like when let's say there are series of events are happening and you want to
execute after user even stop after some time then you that particular process is
called debouncing okay fine I hope now after this I'll say that do you
understand know how async programming work async is something like parallel
whenever you see here this word in cope in programming context you can
understand this as a parallel now in JS since it is a single threaded we don't
have like we have right we can write a multiple multi-threading code logics but
we have something like this mechanism where the costly events are removed from
call stack put somewhere else and only will be executed when it needed to be
that's how we were able to handle costly events like multi-threading concept is
there some proper syntax to deep on so that I can least remember I'll check for
documentation some bit if you see let's say if I go and check for debounce there
might be some use cases but we have to see like if you see this is the same
logic that I used it they are also using function apply this we have to
understand why they are using it but they are also explaining the same
problem using input type text okay but I'll come to that I'll check and I'll
give you a snapshot of a code which can be used for understanding it I try to
pick the very really simple example it's like a three piece of code which is
actually changing it but I hope this debounce is clear okay we'll move on to
the trottling now okay let me let's say I have a new file called trottling dot
HTML and I what I'll do is I'll copy this code I'll paste it here and let me
say that throttling optimized function and I'll call back here and something
that I have to change the logic is in logic is this one like we'll change we'll
be changing the logic here okay but I'll come firstly let's understand what
throttling does and what how does it affect now let's go to flipkart itself
so guys how many of you understand there's something that lazy loading
lazy loading have you heard this keyword lazy loading lazy loading I see three
thumbs down no worries case so let's say a website right a website like flipkart
Netflix they have too much of content right too much of content when you
launch it when you open their sites do you agree with this point like too many
when I say content images images can be heavy in size and the content like the
paragraph contents and everything do you guys agree with that with this part do
you agree at least okay now what happens is to the websites right to optimize to
optimize the page load time okay to optimize page load time page load time
they use one of the concept called lazy loading now the lazy loading is applied
for only costly operations one of the example is that images images are costly
so even when you are pulling from the network they do it only when it is
required when I say when it is required let's say the flipkart page is too long
in nature okay but your viewport view view width is this one so view height is
this one and view width is this much okay this is a screen size you have but
only if you if I load only this part of content when user launch that would be
enough right to show initially whatever your screen is there mobile now then
there is a scroll scroll event is happening here on the left side and
whenever we are scrolling it below do you remember sometimes there's a flashy
images happening like that images keep loading slowly there would be like
animation that you see have you seen any time in your like when you scroll it
suddenly its speed rate you won't see the web page loaded previously but it
keeps on loading it now that is where we say we are loading lazy look we are
easily loading the content I mean we are too much lazy that will load it at a
time so that when you scroll it right API calls are being made to fetch these
images in YouTube in any website in heavy websites where there's a too much
content lazy loading is one of the most opting used concept in order to reduce
the page load time because we will load only whatever required assets are and
then after when user scrolls it depending on whether he's scroll till
here we load this content when he's called here will load this content and
once they loaded they cache it when I say cache it they store here in the
storages so that you again if user goes up and down then don't need to again
load it let's see this in real time let's say that if I go to YouTube okay
no let's say this do you see this this part of thing is loaded like this are
12 boxes nice this 12 boxes now suddenly if I load it do you see this blocks are
getting filled suddenly there was a shade there if I suddenly loaded there's
a shade then the color pictures are coming then the thumbnails are coming
actually do you see this if I load it the below pictures are you able to see
this case no again I'll show you why let's say I go for the inspect if you
see in the network you see in the network
can I okay now let's see what happens when I scroll too many API calls in
YouTube to know but let's say if I scroll it do you see there are pending
requests which are getting fulfilled to fetch the images all this like events
and the images if you see this image this might be the image for something
some YouTube hedge clips or this is you know Aditya music or different images
are being fetched at runtime now this image is let's say Amazon image there
might be somewhere this this person's image okay 80 this one so all these are
thumbnails which are like let's say this one stack versus heap some video may be
content now this person's image so this is somewhere somewhat called as lazy
loading this concept is lazy loading what they're doing it is that only I
loaded only I loaded whatever content is needed one shot and when users cross it
I'll hope I'll like you know I'll do a figure out now you can always figure out
this one what are the listeners attached name if you want to go like you go to
here you know in this you can go to scroll event and explore like what are
the events that are attached okay multiple events you'll see that on page
level if you remove it or this thing will you know stop working whatever you
see that API calls being triggered if you remove it it will stop working okay
there might be many things they might be using it but these are the list of
events you can play around with mouse over key up key down right input element
drag enter drag leave double flick so these are the events that you can see
like what events are attached to your website okay so now coming back here so
I did you understand lazy loading give a thumbs up if you understand now what
lazy loading is how that works no now let's say now let's say what's happening
if I do it again on the flipkart do you see let's say how many pay cost did they
make if you see this they are trying to get fetch the page page numbers now if
you see each page only one page right I had only one page but that page was
divided into multiple pages according to the viewport size do you see this like
let me refresh this one this website and I'll show it okay there might be
somewhere with the API call might have been already made they fetched images
and everything it one shot to loads of you put size images now once I make
now do you see this this this thing made a API call to get the other list of
items of page number two and also it fetched one of the image okay now what
if I go into one section let's say if I go into one section called mobiles let's
say if we have I scroll it down I keep on scrolling now if you see images are
runtime fetch is being made okay let's say the event actually okay these are
like all things are lazily loaded that's what I wanted to show that this is the
real-time concept that whatever we are learning now here just lazy loading is
actually being done using something called as throttling mechanism okay now
let's understand what actually throttling is how we can leverage throttling when
you come to this car like you know lazy loading now what's happening
here would you see on the web page when you reach a particular point when you
scroll up to some extent let's say some height some height of web page that
triggering API call right do you guys agree with this point that that trot
like when you move to the particular height of it they are making a pickle so
now imagine imagine what if this is one of the example like how do you do it
then imagine there is a submit button then this let's say there is a submit
button you created a form you have multiple elements you have filled all
the events then you have a submit button
what if user keep on banging this button each time they keep on pressing this
button again again again again he keep on clicking this button again and again
even then we are making hitting multiple API calls right right like whenever user
is trying to submit a form and he is clicking on submit event again and again
you are trying to hit for on each submit you are making an API call here also what
if user scrolls to this height you make an API call again you go down again you
go up you again make an API call so if you keep on scrolling in a list of API
calls will be happening each time right are you guys do you guys agree with my
point that what I'm talking here like like the user behavior whatever user is
trying to write in order to stop that events are happy for you know triggering
now what we'll do is that once user clicks any event or once user comes to
this crawl we wait for some time
I mean wait till the event happens and then trigger API call okay
it some intervals now when I'm why I'm saying some intervals is let's say this
particular concept also applies it's like same like a debouncing but
debouncing works only like let's say of that input example try to remember like
one example for each one now when you go for input example what was happening is
that we were trying to debounce like we were waiting till user stops once user
stopped I stop it then after we were initiating thus time then we were
initiating the delay and then only we were triggering API call here it doesn't
happen that way once you reach an event API call will be triggered for surely
but after that it will be triggered after again some amount of time it will
be keep on like this works like an interval okay
trottling works like interval where you are trying to reduce the amount of API
calls but it will keep on execute you can make n number of calls okay let me
show you the first let me let us show see this example again okay I'll launch
this one firstly let's say we have this let's I return this function
console dot log instead of console dot log I have to return something like set
timeout again function comma deal nothing much so let's say we are still
executing that same problem if I keep on timing executing it you'll be able to
see all the network calls here okay did I load the wrong file let me load this
throttling let me go back here load this one now I have typed on waiting and
should be executing all the requests this is again going back to that same
problem guys now but what if I what I want to do it here is that I want to
throttle when I when I when I say that let's say when I say this meaning of
throttle is like once user event is click event is clicked our event
happens
throttle the request I mean wait for some time before you execute let let me show
that how that works before I write down anything okay let's see how what happens
here so now when I want to throttle it what I'll do it here is that let's say I
have a flag let's I say that a flag equal to true okay and only when this
flag is true only flag is true I'll do what I'll do is that I'll call this
function whatever function I'm getting I'll execute that function okay and then
I'll make this flag as false now what I'm just doing is that oh just simple
condition let's say I remove this one as of now what I'll do is that simply I'll
check I'll call this function callback function and checking that either the
flag is true and if it is only true then not equally okay triple equal to yeah
triple equal to when only is equal to true then I'll execute the function and
then update flag as false now let's say I also want to update here what I'll do
is that I'll write a set time or logic here not inside this callback function
what I'll do is that I'll give some delay now let's say this delay we are
something we're getting is from the top I have this delay and what I after this
each time delay I'll come convert this into true no what's happening here just
let's figure out if we go from this flow right once the first your trigger this
trottling for callback function let's it is initialized as a true so the function
will be executed at first shot and let me move this inside this one no first
shot the function will be like called and executed then we are making it as a
flag now even after user like when we are calling a set delay okay but user is
keep on pressing some buttons but if we keep on pressing this flag is converted
into false already by here and we won't be triggering this function again again
we won't be calling this function again again till this set time mode executes
and may convert that flag into true
nice are you able to understand what we mean to say that trottel is once user
event happens after one once API call is triggered and we won't trigger an
another API call till there is some delay executed and that delay will define in
the configuration itself so we are trying to rate limit the number of API
calls that will be caught okay let's see this example firstly what I am trying to
say is that let's say I click some bits three-party no I have what let me see
what is a delay I gave 500 milliseconds let's say I give one one second okay or
let's say I make it two seconds I said typed on my name do you see only two API
calls have been made for considering this one the reason here why it happened
is firstly let me go into this logic let me put debuggers and show you two guys
how this works okay now what if I type down again now once let's say clean it
up
let's say I typed on you here once I typed on you now a flag is already true
and it will execute that function and that will put a call API call it will
hit an API call and then we are calling a set timeout okay and this set timeout
will execute only after two seconds of delay okay till then if I typed on
anything if that flag will be false so it won't execute go inside it anything
then once the timeout is updated the flag will be converted into true from
then on if you type anything new that flag will be true and it will call that
function are able to relate this case like should I debug it again and show it
so what we are generally doing it here is that rate limiting
the API calls now why rate limiting the API call works is if you see the in
YouTube or anything the content of videos this least data right that gets
updated as per your personalization profiles again and again because it's a
multi-day multi-device setup now when I scroll it a list of API calls will be
made okay and this API calls will be again if I what if I go go and scroll up
what if this things are getting updated okay
yeah the function here is something like yeah API call that is what we are
assuming it here this particular function
so guys are you able to relate like rate when I say rate limiting the API calls
like we are limiting the amount of calls that API will be triggered or the
function will be called
yes are you able to follow up or did you like you do you didn't understand it give
me one thumbs up some thumbs up so that I can list down the differences I and
we'll be able to understand like actually what is the difference on like
top level what between the bones and this let's say I write down a list of
things let's say I say that this is for D bonds and this is for throttle okay
which I have a pen this one I say purpose what is the purpose for D bonds
so I'll say this is like for delaying let's say this is like for delaying
delay the function execution
until an activity in activity so if you remember this one we are
dealing a like calling of that function or API call from the input element till
the user stops pressing right key events we didn't execute that call we only
execute once user stops it that delays expired only then we make a if they
call right for D bonds and for throttling what we do is that limit
function execution rate and how we are able to limit the function execution rate
by using the simple condition that first time whenever a pay call comes we
make it true that flag is true by default so that a pic of that function
will be executed then we're converting false and this flag will be again
converted to true only after some delay and this is actually this particular set
time what is actually delaying the second API call till that particular
delay have now okay to show this how this happens let's say user event that's I
typed on graphics for this one user event is like do keep on typing events
no then once he stops it this delay will be we will be waiting for this delay
then function execution will happen here for throttling purpose how does it
happen is once the user event is clicked okay we will call that function and we
will load the delay we load the delay and each even if user is typing it down
we won't make any API calls or function execution only this will be done when
this delay is expired we'll call it again and then we'll wait again for some
delay only then we'll load it this is like a set interval only after once this
call is done we'll wait for an interval then we'll again load it so it is like
limit limiting the rate of execution is this clear guys difference between
debounce and throttle okay now when it comes to execution let me write down in
the statement also
let's say executes
after a pass
in which
whereas this one executes at a steady rate and the steady rate is the delay
that you provided now the third thing is let's say event reset timer so when
this thing happened reset event reset no case can anyone answer this thing for
me when that event reset happened in their debounce like going back to this
example can I say on each event this time it timeout is reset on each event
right on each event whereas this one it maintains steady rate there is no
clearing of timer here are we clearing set timeout here in the throttling we
aren't right we are not clearing this timeout right guys no events no actually
I'll write as a no simply or never okay then let's say if I talk about something
like frequency handling
when I say frequency handling like what actually it is doing it how it is how
once delay is over we are not clearing the events right Shambhuja here for
throttling like we are not calling clear timeout anytime we are just using the
flag we are talking at loading okay so I would request everyone to go through
this examples again try to execute it use this table I'll try to upload this
table also a photo of snapshot of this one in the notes so that you will be
able to remember like the position okay so let's say reduces the function calls
during rapid events
like when user is typing we try to reduce the amount of function calls
right at each rapid event like user is keep on typing the keyword will we have
to wait so we are reducing it so now for this one we can say that limit function
call to set interval we are using an interval and only after that interval
this thing is come now what could be the examples for this one where all
debouncing can be used so debouncing function call will never stop yes
function call will never stop when user is keep on typing it okay when user keep
on scrolling it down the page or anytime like what will do is that whenever that
something is happening a function call will not stop but we will be executing
this thing only when this flag is true we will try to execute that one if not
then we won't execute it and each time for each event we are not even attaching
set timeout for each event we won't be able to attach a set timeout we will be
only able to attach that set timeout only for that first if you attach it then
after only delay then we will be able to attach the timeout for that event okay
now examples would be for this one
typing or let's say search suggestion
okay or let's say even you can consider it as a resizing events now resizing
event might not be covered but what we mean to say resizing is that yeah
some bit will show it in the event loop completely will cover it up now if you
see this this is like a resizing event now when I reduce it or increase it if
you see just seen the YouTube API calls if you see in the YouTube API calls if I
resize if I resize the amount of API calls being made that is those are the
resize event for the resizing events also use something like a debouncing
concept okay or in when it comes to throttling you use it for scrolling
mouse events like mouse events mouse over or mouse when you remove it right
the rate limited API's okay so these are the differences guys that you should be
able to remember I'll also add a like actual photo or like you know image
that I made it for position so that you will be able to remember it and I'll try
to add diagrams as much as possible to so that you can figure it out how set
timeout on set interval is working behind the scenes but on let me know if
you are able to relate with this statements first if you are able to
understand this points any doubts till now from the code perspective or logic
perspective I picked it up one sort of example because it should be easy when
you come and see that how this what's the difference between debouncing
throttling it just that at one place we are clearing all the previous events and
then only if we are attaching to the last most user typed event where is
coming to throttling we are not even attaching the set timeout for the all
the things you are too much to process I agree but this is this other you know
if you see the problem these people these two things are solving are big
things and you will be able to process it slowly and you'll get complete
clarity over this one okay but now I have one of the small topic to cover
guys I will talk about that one okay now let's go to some other again big
websites itself I go to this YouTube itself I come here in the head tag now
inside the head tag let's see do I have any scripts present say I say it's
defer
I didn't highlight the defer
okay anyways let's see it in the flipkart inside the head this is metadata
related no guys do you see this keyword here differ in the script tag this
keyword differ no this is really simple guys I'll cover it up not much big
thing it will like just a content part because debouncing throttling will keep
on revising again again so that you will be comfortable with that okay today's
content right so we have to cover this is 10 minutes hardly will complete it to
16 okay so no till now whenever we return in HTML files right whenever we
return something in HTML when we are tracking any scripts files or CSS files
we were giving source and most probably relation right for CSS files other than
this thing we were not providing anything but in general at real time you
have three types of scripts one is simple script one is having something
like async script and then there is something like differ script okay let me
say these are the things which are existing now we know that even HTML is
loaded from top to down isn't it like executed from top to down and whenever
we load script anywhere in head that script sometimes like if you remember
font awesome right font awesome we were linking in the head section right when
we are linking in the head section that font awesome code should be downloaded
right font awesome code should be downloaded before we use it in HTML part
inside the body you know because that that is what we are doing now if you
want to do it that way and if it is happening from top to bottom imagine if
font awesome site is down whether our HTML will be passed after this or it
will be blocked what if that CDN link whatever CDN link we have that website
downloading I mean it yeah so what I mean to say that it's like let's say
font awesome link whatever script we got it from a CDN link now when the HTML is
being passed from top to down and once we find that there's a script tag
related to font awesome and we are trying to get fetch the data from the
CDN whatever JS code they have written and if this CDN is on JS the passing of
HTML would go to the next step it will try to fetch it again okay because this
will be blocked and even if CDN is not down it is too slow what if it's low the
code execution will be blocked at that particular step in the script okay so how
does it happen is let's say this is a timeline in which HTML is being passed
let's say you got a boar head tag here right here is ending the head and you
saw the script related to font awesome now once you saw this font awesome if
the site is slow or down the other parts of code execution will be blocked this is
blocked because we are trying to interact with something which is slow
are you able to understand this one guys now like when you load simple script
what are the challenges you can have when you load on inside the head no the
workaround what we have seen that is something that you can load it at the
end of the body at the end of the body you can do it very well end of the body
only if you have custom written JS logic but if you have something like font
awesome and this particular HTML inside the body tag we are using those icons
then we need this one to be pre downloaded right that logic for that
icon should be pre downloaded those tags so what was a solution provided for this
one was use two types of attributes one is something called async and one is
what async does is let's see I'll write down for async now what we understood by
this keyword earlier what does async says parallel execution isn't it
asynchronous programming or async when you see that pulling out from the call
stack putting into the queue right same way what happens here is let's say this
is a timeline still and once you passing comes to the head it finds a script what
it says is that hey I found a script that needs a time to download so what
will say that it will download separately that script download will
happen but it won't block the queue when you use async keyword it will keep on
executing the other parts of code so parallelly the HTML will be passed in
parallel JS code will be downloaded and once this is downloaded right once this
is downloading is completed then this particular code will be blocked and this
will be executed first then again HTML parsing will happen is this clear when
you use async word in general you are trying to parallelly execute that script
tag fetch the data from the internet parallelly execute that HTML meanwhile
only once this data is downloaded then you execute that JS and then you have to
again pass the HTML is this clear guys how what async keyword in the script tag
does they have received only one thumbs up maybe few more if not clear I can
repeat in the next class also okay then you have something like defer what does
differ does is there's only one change there's only one change that differ and
async have is that once you find a head again you locate that script tag like a
font does some script it will also download it it will also download in
parallel it will also download that script tag in parallel
okay it will download it but till the whole HTML is parsed till whole HTML is
passed this won't be passed once the HTML is passed this will be passed JS
will be passed what was happening in async as soon as download is completed
this was being passed in between itself then again HTML was passing and all
this can happen only one thing at a time because that we have single threaded and
in single threaded environment only one thing can happen at a one time and this
script download is also being put from the call stack put it into some queue
and once this is download is done once this download is done this was put into
the call stack again right that passing is happening then once that is done
that HTML is passed but here only the difference in with defer is till that
HTML is completely pass it won't interrupt once that the passing is done
only then this will be added is this clear guys what is difference between
simple script and script with async keyword script with defer keyword parallel
download instant parsing and this is blocking in nature and this is also
blocking in nature parallel download and wait till HTML is passed this is
non-blocking in nature I still HTML passing I don't use word execution here
consider it as passing okay now if you go to any website if you go to any
website and see you will be almost seeing the differ keyword used more than
the async keyword this particular all this thing sites right they are waiting
to completely this below things are getting completely like you know past
once these are done only then this will be fast because these are you know
static images these are static images they're getting from the CDN if you go
and try to you know see this there might be a URL for this one where they're
getting assets static assets if you see so they're waiting for all this logic
yeah notes okay so guys is this clear like or do I need to repeat it again
somewhere did you get that point did you understand this one or do I need to
repeat again okay I'll repeat it again so guys what is happening in real time
is like script tax since this script tax mostly are used for you know getting
the JS code the JS code can be in the size of KBs MBs sometimes MB sometime
KBs okay now when your HTML like if you remember are we have HTML then we have
head then we have body then we close HTML right this is what our body
structure is but in head tag if we have this JS scripts right we have defined it
and whenever we have like such amount of size KB and MB of size right now to
download this data from network it takes time and we know that HTML will be
passed only from top to down and when we you know when we find there's a script
which is downloading JavaScript which are in size of KB and MB it will stop
the execution below execution it will block the thread it will block the
thread which is single threaded right so it will block the thread and it the
particular thing will be downloaded will be passed and only then the below
things will be passed this is how normally naturally works but async one
what happened with async keyword is once we have HTML head body HTML again
closing so once you find the script it says that hey you download parallely
download in parallel till this download is happening I'll keep on executing
HTML once this download is done this will be blocked this will be execute
passed first right then again this will continue with async whereas what
differ says is doesn't matter
whatever it is you completely pass the HTML then I will pass JS code and
downloading will happen in parallel
so that's the reason why I'm saying that differ tag is like non blocking nature
this both are blocking in nature because these are blocking HTML parsing is this
clear guys now any doubts like when you see this async and differ keyword I hope
can we see in the code how to use this yeah we can do this we can always do
this but in order to do this right you need to have really big files that are
being pulled from the network we don't have real time yeah we can see it in
future uncate it's like I guess we're tired with the content but if you see in
the many websites right you will be able to see the scripts with differ and
async let's say you go for any other website like this one you'll see this
thing being used everywhere you see this script tag is async JavaScript text file
which is like doing that calling this go Google Analytics Google manager dot com
all these things are done in async fashion okay all these four files
whereas you'll also see our differ used okay you'll see this this thing like is
actually fetching the image from the CD and link okay so whichever things that
you think that okay I can I guys like is the if concepts are clear can I start
the doubt session but I hope no no no it doesn't work that way wherever you
define the script it works anywhere in the script like with a script tag with
the script tag wherever you mention in the body below the body anywhere even if
you mention wherever script is there but if you are using something like a
particular HTML tag with async differ that's our nature I'm talking about
nature of this two key attributes like async and differ is that clear okay
great so you can go and see most of the websites right most of the websites what
happens is like this particular like Google Analytics and Google manager this
things right they are like downloaded in async manner all the your respective
code whichever is there like if you see this is a free code camp website all
this free code camp particular related websites are downloaded in a differ mode
because this your respective codes are really what we can say that it might not
be deployed on CDN links they deployed on CDN but it might be on your server so
it takes time to load it or else even your assets will be bigger in size
whereas come to analytics right this need to be loaded at runtime I mean why
they do it at the initial moment of the time is because these are actually
sending multiple events like if you see this is this is not the event but if you
know actually analytics is used to track user events like how much user is
spending on each thing and what not they try to track multiple experimentations
okay for that reason they try to load it as early as possible but when it comes
to the other big files you should prefer the differ keyword okay guys I hope you
understand what is async differ and simple script give me one thumbs up if
this is clear so that I can start doubt session I can clear take the doubts
if you have anything okay good so with this guys I want to end the content for
today's class when we'll meet next class in next class right we'll start with
object-oriented programming we'll take two classes an object-oriented program
will understand how that is being done so it will be more of a behind the
scenes trying to learn JS so I'll try to make it as interesting as possible let
me start doubt session is hope to see you in next class again do you want me
to revise everything guys in doubt session yeah I'll try to make it
interactive ways let's it's really difficult to ask we sunk it here it
doesn't work like the DSA right mostly we'll try to add it as much as possible
right but let's let's go back and revise the content for a second and then okay
what's happening with debounce okay so firstly if we understood two things in
today's class firstly set timeout set interval debouncing and trotting now
timeout works if you want to do a task after some time like delaying it and
execute a particular function a callback function whereas interval it executes a
particular task at each interval okay no so debouncing and throttling you can map
it debouncing to something called a set timeout and you can set throttling to
set interval okay don't exactly think it that way but that's how behind the
scene things works what in the once happens is when user is keep on typing
events we say that we don't want to make all the API calls only once user stops
it we take some delay and the deal is also like we want to wait what if user
again start typing it okay so if he once user stops it we wait for delay and then
we try to execute the function whereas when it comes to throttling we say that
this event can be triggered in number of times like scroll he can do up and down
or it can take the mouse and he can do on there itself like up and down let's
say what do I exactly mean is that let's say if I go to this particular page let's
say the scroll is he at this particular question there triggering API call if I
keep on doing this way the API call will be keep on triggering right behind the
scenes so in order to stop that thing happening we try to reduce the amount of
calls let's say if you see it here what is happening this is if you see this
events right the all the events have one after the other keep on going it let's
say I call it up again so in order to reduce the if there will be many amount
of API calls which are also cancelled okay this events like events are
cancelled to get too many events so this events like why we are why they are
doing it this one is that to throttle it user can you don't try to take
advantage of our services and we'll try to you know do as many requests are as
possible we don't understand exact behavior of human so in order to wait
and do that one right so we try to rate limit the amount of calls we are doing
so for that thing we use throttling what we say that it will make a call first
then again if user is against crawling up and back I won't make a call but I
will make only call after some amount of time so that I'll save the this amount
of API calls being triggered okay so that is how throttling works so trying
to go back to this again definition is that delay the function execution until
activity okay when it comes to this one now when it comes to throttling limiting
the execution rate okay then execute after a pause in events like once user
stops typing and if this executes it's a steady rate all the time till that
moment you are trying to play around and it doesn't mean that it will keep on
executing that call only when events that particular event is triggered in
number of times in those n number of times it will execute three to four
times okay that set interval works only when you are that event is again again
triggered on that same like submit button if you are smashing a submit
button hundred times it will make only three to four API calls doesn't mean
that once you click a submit button it irregular intervals it keep on making an
API call okay now events reset like each time a event is triggered we try to
remove the set time also be on each event reset happens here we don't do it
actually because here we are doing a rate limiting so reduce the function
calls doing that during rapid events here limit function calls to set
interval like that particular interval okay typing and resizing events here when
comes to scrolling a rate limited API's and within we discussed the same thing
I hope this part is anyways clear so there's any doubts I know this might be
overwhelming but I'll again are we going to use this in projects in future yeah
I'll give you one a little question some bit which is really important to them
okay let's say
this question right type at component if you see how many people might have
covered four or five people have covered in the YouTube no if and if you go this
to this one right they might have built this one using Google example now you if
you see this one they'll show you the architecture and complete like how do
you are using it how do you are making a call so this is actually an important
interview question to develop this widget I'll see if this is widget exist
because you have to build this end-to-end let me see if I can build and
give it to you okay but I don't want to do it because I just want to cover the
content which is assigned it maybe other than that one I have to let's do one
thing if someone can build you know LLD repo which ones I'll also contribute in
that okay if you have questions I can also contribute in that but if you see
there are too many let's say this is a Chirag's one this is he's a
constructor it's scalar most senior front-end developer that I know L64
at Microsoft but if you see he have this question this link I will try to give
his link you can go through this one where he has explained this okay
but I was actually searching for some content they are stopping me from even
I'm longing and why didn't all over
sign up okay cool now this is actually explained from behind the you know back
and high level design where you are using a try logic and trying to
understand how do you do searching actually once user query set but we are
trying to you know reduce the amount of queries that are done firstly on the
front-end right let's say type at react
let's say we have front-end LLD
autocomplete if you see this is the example they again this is leading to
the same website but they are actually again doing it from the back end because
they are talking about data model caching mechanism okay client okay
they're given events all the humans that you listen to now if you see they are
talking about debounce timing how much the bonds timing you need so this is the
same they are using but we have to build this one completely from scratch in order
to do that we have to explore this one so they used caches they replicated a
API call and what will be the result so end-to-end complete like you know
let's say I can say I say put strap components the accordion everything is
auto search auto search react MUI now if you see I keep on typing let's say let's
say if you have this list of items which are pre-rendered right now this list of
item suggestions are are actually you have stored on the client side what if
you want to get on from the server side that's when you actually have to reduce
it but they haven't given here I'll search and I'll give it to you like how
can you build this autocomplete completely but we should be building this
one this is one of the most in the interview important question interview
some bit try to focus like how can you leverage debouncing and I'll check on
which site is better content like which is providing us better content like let
me say bit.dev because everywhere that same logic will be that this is a
generic function that is applied for debounce okay debounce is also you get
sometimes but it's not a built-in function but you write one function
generically and you use this everywhere I think this is the thing they have
anyways I'll check on I'll get you I should be a better side right to
understand it anyways I'll repeat for my side the time should you want they have
also given a good you know a reference for this one but if you want if you want
to understand this this keyword right we'll pick it up in next class because
without this understanding this you won't be able to understand okay they
this with this definition will confuse you don't go by this educative site
guys if there are no doubts can we in the session some bit this is it I
believe like you know this is it this is the thing they have you know common
there's a callback function and a delay function the same logic that we have
written I've seen it more than five six sites this is how they are handling but
I'll talk about this how you know spreading you know spread operator and
ask what what they actually meant it now this is actually being done only when
you want to process events right when you want to process the events there we
were getting that we didn't get the events right we can even get those
events the way you can do that one is let's say you have events okay and let's
say you call this okay inside this let's say you also pass on the event here you
will be able to access at runtime all the events will be here and you can pass
it on to the down the chain but wherever you want to use it and this will work
like a function I mean callback function attachment then you can return directly
instead of calling it as a function that that use case also you can handle it
okay let me push the code meanwhile do you guys find it heavy content today it
was it was it heavy to understand but you know do revise this concept try to
read it try to I'll make a notes for this one so that I attach a image or you
can refer to it completely new concept I agree this is first time even when I
studied I was like what is this but it takes time to digest it okay but these
are like one of the core you know principles when you want to optimize
a network calls or optimize the page load time so these are something that
you're going to do enhancements on your websites which you build because you
want to delay all the assets loading right how you want to you don't want to
do it everything at one shot you have to break down your problem and do it at
different so then this concepts will come in and you want how you will be
able to handle it okay so guys I don't see any doubts with that I would like to
end the today's session and we'll meet you back on Tuesday where we'll get to
learn more interesting things like we'll see like what ES6 team has done
converting a functional language into object-oriented language we'll see like
does it actually JavaScript support from the object-oriented programming or is it
something they tried to fake it out we'll come back and we'll explore that
one okay guys so the rest with that hope you have a good night take care happy
weekend see you on Tuesday bye bye
this can be in the session give me one final thumbs up cool so the rest is
right thanks some bits
you